---
title: "1.6.12. Ship's Agents and Agency"
read_title: "Ship's Agents and Agency"
slug: "lesson-1"
estimated_hours: 2
learning_outcomes:
  - to analyse UNCTAD's Minimum Standards for Shipping Agents
  - to distinguish between general and special agents
  - to categorise types of shipping agents according to their duties
  - to separate the work of shipping agents
  - to distinguish shipping agents' rights and duties
  - to analyse Maritime agency agreement.

links:
  - "[UNCTAD Minimum Standards for Shipping Agents](https://unctad.org/system/files/official-document/unctadstship13_en.pdf)"
  - "[The Federation of National Associations of Ship Brokers and Agents (FONASBA)](https://www.fonasba.com/)"
  - "[FONASBA Quality Standard](https://www.fonasba.com/fonasba-initiatives/fonasba-quality-standard)"
  - "[FONASBA Documentation](https://www.fonasba.com/documentation)"

literature:
  - Drago Pavić, Pomorsko imovinsko pravo, Književni krug, Split, 2006
  - Nikola Mandić – Ivana Lovrić, Pomorske agencije i otpremništvo, Pomorski fakultet, Split, 2019
  - Regulations on Conditions Required to Conduct the Activity of the Maritime Agent and Rights and Duties of the Maritime Agent, Official Gazette, no. 82/07 (Pravilnik o uvjetima za obavljanje djelatnosti pomorskog agenta, te pravima i obvezama pomorskog agenta, Narodne novine, br. 82/07.) – [https://asbac.hr/wp-content/dokumenti/pravilnici/uvjeti_za_obavljanje_djelatnosti.pdf](https://asbac.hr/wp-content/dokumenti/pravilnici/uvjeti_za_obavljanje_djelatnosti.pdf)

quiz:
  - question: "The shipping agent can be:"
    options:
      - "Only legal person"
      - "Only natural person"
      - "Legal and natural person"
    correct_answer: 2
  - question: "The shipping agent performs representation and mediation services in maritime business:"
    options:
      - "In his own name and on behalf of the principal"
      - "In the name and on behalf of the principal"
      - "On his behalf but in the name of the principal"
      - "In his own name and on his behalf"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "Concluding services in another's name and on another's behalf means that they:"
    options:
      - "Do not bind the principal, but only the shipping agent"
      - "Bind both the principal and the shipping agent within the scope of the obligations assumed"
      - "They do not bind the shipping agent, but directly his principal"
    correct_answer: 2
  - question: "The shipping agent is not a party to the contracts concluded through his mediation, but rather his principal."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 0
  - question: "Only the shipowner is authorised to appoint a shipping agent."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "A shipping agent acting in ports is called:"
    options:
      - "Port agent"
      - "An intermediary agent"
      - "Cargo agent"
      - "Insurance agent"
    correct_answer: 0
  - question: "A shipping agent who mediates and represents his charterer when concluding various contracts is called:"
    options:
      - "Port agent"
      - "An intermediary agent"
      - "Cargo agent"
      - "Insurance agent"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "A shipping agent who continuously analyzes the market, predicts trends and monitors the demand for shipping space and the supply of cargo for transport is called:"
    options:
      - "Port agent"
      - "An intermediary agent"
      - "Cargo agent"
      - "Insurance agent"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "A shipping agent acting on the basis of a general power of attorney is considered to be:"
    options:
      - "Agent with unlimited powers"
      - "Agent with limited powers"
      - "General agent"
      - "Special agent"
    correct_answer: 2
  - question: "The powers of the general agent, given by the maritime agency agreement are always limited in time and not of a permanent nature."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "In case of disagreement between the master of the ship and the shipping agent, it is considered that priority should be given to:"
    options:
      - "Shipping agent"
      - "Master of the ship"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "The parties to the maritime agency agreement are:"
    options:
      - "Principal (shipper/shipowner) and charterer"
      - "Charterer and shipping agent"
      - "Principal (shipper/shipowner) and shipping agent"
    correct_answer: 2
  - question: "The minimum standards for shipping agents were adopted in 1988 in order to harmonize the standards of shipping agents and to prevent maritime fraud, and were adopted by:"
    options:
      - "The Federation of National Associations of Ship Brokers and Agents."
      - "UN Conference on Trade and Development"
      - "Multiport network of maritime agencies"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "UNCTAD's Minimum Standards for Shipping Agents:"
    options:
      - "Govern the content and template for concluding maritime agency agreement"
      - "Prescribes business ethics and professional conduct for shipping agents"
      - "Prescribes FONASBA quality standards for shipping agents"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "UNCTAD's Minimum Standards for Shipping Agents is a mandatory guideline for national authorities and professional associations of shipping agents when developing their own national standards."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "The study of the legal status of shipping agents, in particular their standardization in the legislation of individual countries and the rules governing their work and conduct at international level, is actively pursued by:"
    options:
      - "The Federation of National Associations of Ship Brokers and Agents"
      - "UN Conference on Trade and Development"
      - "Multiport network of maritime agencies"
    correct_answer: 0
  - question: "The set of standards developed by the Federation of National Associations of Ship Brokers and Agents in 2007 to provide the maritime industry with a robust, enforceable and practical standard of quality and to help ensure that the activities, responsibilities and obligations of shipping agents and brokers are subject to control is called:"
    options:
      - "FIATA quality standard"
      - "FONASBA quality standard"
      - "EUROCREW quality standard"
      - "MULTIPORT quality standard"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "The liner shipping company and the general agent for the exercise of the general agency activity in the territory on the basis of which the general agent is authorized to act as agent for the principal in a certain area, conclude:"
    options:
      - "General agency agreement (for liner services) 1993"
      - "General agency agreement 2017"
      - "Agency appointment agreement 2017"
    correct_answer: 0
  - question: "To appoint an agent for a longer period of time and for a larger range of ports, the following is concluded:"
    options:
      - "General agency agreement (for liner services) 1993"
      - "General agency agreement 2017"
      - "Agency appointment agreement 2017"
    correct_answer: 1
  - question: "To appoint an agent for a small number of ports, the following is concluded:"
    options:
      - "General agency agreement (for liner services) 1993"
      - "General agency agreement 2017"
      - "Agency appointment agreement 2017"
    correct_answer: 2
---

**Shipping agent** is a legel or natural person who, on the basis of a general or special power of attorney, performs maritime agency services, i.e. representation, mediation and assistance based on a maritime agency agreement. **Maritime agency** services include above all, activities in connection with shipping, ships and their use, the crew and in particular: acceptance and clearance of ships, mediation in the conclusion of contracts for the use of ships, purchase and sale, construction, modification and repair of ships, insurance of ships, cargo and interest, provision of supplies and care of passengers and crew.

Shipping agent is not an employee of his principal (who is usually the shipowner or a shipper, but can also be other person), but performs the work of a maritime agency based on maritime agency agreement concluded with the principal. The shipping agent carries out its activities in the name and on behalf of its principal. This means that the agent is not a party to the contracts concluded through his mediation but is his principal.
By means of the **Maritime agency agreement**, the shipping agent undertakes, on the basis of a general or special power of attorney, to carry out agency jobs in the name and on behalf of the principal, i.e. representation, mediation and assistance, and the principal undertakes to pay the shipping agent an expense allowance and remuneration.

When carrying out his activities, the shipping agent is obliged to indicate that he is acting in the capacity of an agent. Otherwise, in relation to a third person in good faith, he is considered acting on his own behalf. For this reason, it is written next to the signature of the shipping agent in contracts that he is acting in the name and on behalf of or as an agent only.

The shipping agent is **obliged** and authorized to perform the tasks necessary or customary for the execution of the order received with due care within the scope of the power of attorney granted. Within the framework of the contractual relationship with the shipping agent, a certain degree of professional diligence is required to protect the interests of the other party. The shipping agent is obliged to protect the interests of the principal and to act with the care of a good businessperson in all work he performs. He is obliged to protect the business secrets of his principal, which he learned in connection with the work, entrusted to him.

The shipping agent is entitled to reimbursement of costs and a reward for arranging and concluding the contract.

Depending on the scope of the powers, shipping agents are divided into **general** and s**pecial agents**. The powers of the general agent, which he receives within the framework of the maritime agency agreement, are usually unlimited in time and of a permanent nature. The special port agent, on the other hand, is authorised to act from one case to another and unlike the general agent, his authority is not permanent.

Depending on the tasks performed by shipping agents, they are divided into port agents, intermediary agents, cargo agents and insurance agents. The most important distinction is between port agents and intermediary agents.

**A port agent** is an agent who acts in ports outside the headquarters of the shipping company and performs all administrative and commercial tasks for the shipowner as part of the regular operation of the ship. The activity of the port agent consists of the provision of various services in the execution of tasks that should be performed in the port of loading or unloading in connection with the ship by the shipowner or the master of the ship. These include various commercial and administrative-legal tasks such as completing formalities for the entering the port, obtaining berths in the port of loading or unloading cargo, organizing berthing, pilot and towage services, informing interested parties of the ship's arrival, completing formalities with customs, port, shipping and health authorities, issuing transport and other documents relating to the ship and cargo, calculating and collecting freight charges, receiving and handing over protests and complaints to the ship, organizing damage surveys, obtaining a guarantee for the payment of a contribution to a general average or salvage premium, organizing sanitary measures in connection with the ship (e.g. disinfect the ship), removing waste from the ship, assisting the master during the ship's stay in port with the execution of contracts of carriage by sea, looking after the crew (ensuring health care, embarkation, disembarkation and temporary accommodation) supplying the ship with food, essential goods and fuel and performing a range of other tasks relating to the cargo and the ship. In the case of passenger ships, the shipping agent takes care of everything that is important for the embarkation and disembarkation of passengers.

**An intermediary agent** is a person who mediates and represents his principal in the conclusion of various jobs. These activities are: mediation and representation in the conclusion of contracts for the use of the ship, contracts for the purchase and sale of vessels, contracts for the construction, modification and repair of vessels, mediation in the allocation of shipping space on behalf of shipowners or transport customers, mediation in the procurement of cargo, mediation in the loading of cargo, mediation in the employment of seafarers, etc. Specialized companies act as an intermediary agent, monitoring the situation on the global shipping market and looking for the most favourable conditions for clients (shippers or charterers).

In 1988, the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD) adopted the **Minimum Standards for Shipping Agents**, which prescribe the business ethics and professional conduct of shipping agents. These are optional guidelines for national authorities and professional associations of shipping agents in developing their own national standards.

The Federation of National Associations of Ship Brokers and Agents (FONASBA) was founded in 1969 in London. Today, the national associations of shipping agents of all Western European maritime states, most member states of the European Union and the biggest shipping states in the world are members of FONASBA. FONASBA is actively engaged in the study of the legal status of shipping agents, in particular their standardization in the legislation of individual countries and the rules governing their work and conduct. In order to protect the interests of shipowners, FONASBA developed a set of standards in 2007, the so-called FONASBA Quality Standard, which raises and unifies the standards for the profession of shipping agent.
